{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This non-Egyptian state was founded by Qutb al-Din Aibak, a Mamluk who succeeded Muhammad of Ghor. The general Zafar Khan established the breakaway Bahmani Sultanate after a revolt against this state. A member of the Tughlaq Dynasty, Muhammad, attempted to shift its capital to the Deccan Plateau. This state was defeated by Babur at the First Battle of Panipat, causing it to be succeeded by the Mughal Empire. For ten points, name this Muslim state that ruled much of India from a namesake city.",
      "answer": "Delhi Sultanate"
    },
    {
      "question": "On April 13, 2016, this player went 22 for 50 from the field, scoring 60 points against the Utah Jazz to end the worst season in franchise history and his career. This man, who won an Oscar in 2018 for Best Animated Short Film for Dear Basketball, scored 81 points against the Raptors in 2006. For ten points, name this shooting guard who won five NBA titles with the Los Angeles Lakers in the early 2000s.",
      "answer": "Kobe Bryant"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler survived an assassination attempt by Giuseppe Fieschi. Early in his life, this ruler fled to Austria with Charles Dumouriez. This monarch’s reign saw the death of Jean Lamarque result in the June Rebellion, and his foreign minister was Francois Guizot. This monarch rose to power during the July Revolution of 1830 that deposed Charles X, and was succeeded by Napoleon III. For ten points, name this citizen king of France.",
      "answer": "Louis Philippe I"
    },
    {
      "question": "One essay concerning this region includes chapters named for the Ohio and Mississippi Valleys; that essay, which was originally introduced during the World’s Columbian Exposition, formed the basis of Frederick Jackson Turner’s thesis on this region. In 1890, the U.S Census Bureau stated that rapid western expansion had “closed” this region. For ten points, name this region which was traditionally considered to be the Western United States.",
      "answer": "American Frontier"
    },
    {
      "question": "This thinker wrote that religion was the result of an “oceanic feeling” in one work, and in another work he analyzed the “death drive.” This author of Civilization and its Discontents and Beyond the Pleasure Principle theorized about the subconscious desire for one’s mother, which he called the “Oedipus complex.” For ten points, name this Austrian thinker who coined the terms “Id,” “ego,” and “superego,” the father of psychoanalysis.",
      "answer": "Sigmund Freud IHO General Bowl 2017-2018 Round 9"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man defeated the Medians at the Halys River before fighting an indecisive battle with the Persians at Pteria. Cyrus the Great destroyed this man’s kingdom at the Battle of Thymbra before besieging this man’s capital of Sardis. According to Herodotus, this man asked Solon who the happiest man in the world was before sending him away for saying it was not him. This man issued the world’s first gold coins. For ten points, name this famously wealthy King of Lydia.",
      "answer": "Croesus"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event’s participants clashed with Khamba rebels, who were escaping from a failed revolt in Tibet. This event’s planners sought to link up with He Long after Mo Xiong brought news of an impending attack. Otto Braun’s wish to travel east was overruled during this event’s Zunyi Conference, which took place shortly before a crossing at Luding Bridge. Participants in this campaign narrowly escaped destruction from the Encirclement Campaigns by traveling north to Shaanxi. For ten points, name this 1934 military retreat undertaken by Mao Zedong’s Chinese Communists.",
      "answer": "Long March"
    },
    {
      "question": "This state’s Pillar Mountain contains an antenna farm for communication between one of its islands and the mainland. The Knick arm is one branch of inlet that stretches to the most-populous city in this state that is the Cook Inlet. In 1964, more than 100 people in this state died in a tsunami triggered by a 9.2 magnitude earthquake on Good Friday; that earthquake devastated Kodiak and Prince William Sound. For ten points, name this US state that contains the Aleutian Islands and the city of Anchorage.",
      "answer": "Alaska"
    },
    {
      "question": "Nicolaes Couckebacker provided naval support to an army facing an uprising led by followers of this religion. The San Felipe incident resulted in the execution of twenty-six members of this religion. The 16-year old Amakusa Shiro helped take over Hara Castle during a 1637 to 1638 uprising involving members of this religion known as the Shimabara Rebellion. That rebellion by members of this religion resulted in a stronger enforcement of sakoku isolationism. For ten points, name this religion that was brought to Japan by Portuguese missionaries.",
      "answer": [
        "Christianity",
        "Roman Catholic Church"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Merchants in this city called pochteca were exempt from paying taxes, instead having to donate to a ritual feast each year. This city was home to the Templo Mayor, a massive complex located in the Sacred Precinct. A massacre at this city’s “Great Temple” led citizens to drive out Pedro de Alvarado as part of La Noche Triste. This city was founded after settlers saw an eagle atop a cactus with a snake in its mouth. Hernan Cortes conquered, for ten points, what capital of the Aztec Empire?",
      "answer": "Tenochtitlan IHO General Bowl 2017-2018 Round 9"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was named heir after the revolt of Casperius Aelianus. This man annexed the Nabataean Kingdom and captured Ctesiphon from the Parthians. His architect Apollodorus of Damascus built a massive bridge across the Danube as part of a war against Decebalus that ended with the capture of Sarmizegetusa. The forum and market built during his lifetime survive to today. This ruler celebrated his Dacian campaign with his namesake column. For ten points, name this Roman emperor, succeeded by Hadrian, who brought Rome to its greatest extent.",
        "answer": "Trajan BONUS:Thisman,thegovernorofBithynia,wroteseveralletterstoTrajanaskingforadviceingoverning, one of which dealt with Christians. ANSWER: Pliny the Younger"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tanganyika is the second oldest and second deepest lake in the world; this Siberian lake is the world’s oldest and deepest.",
        "answer": "Lake Baikal"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A revolt in this region began after fears it would lose the toleration granted to it in the “Letter of Majesty” of Rudolf II; that revolt featured an early capture of Pilsen by the forces of Ernst von Mansfeld. A ruler of this region, Frederick the Winter King, was defeated by Count Tilly at the Battle of White Mountain near its capital, which was earlier the site of an incident in which 2 Catholic ambassadors were tossed out of a window. For ten points, name this Czech region whose capital is Prague.",
        "answer": "Bohemia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Austrian troops moving against the Bohemian Revolt were aided by Ambrogio Spinola, who was depicted in what Diego Velasquez painting showing a battle in the Eighty Years War?",
        "answer": "The Surrender of Breda IHO General Bowl 2017-2018 Round 9"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A slave born on this man’s estate attempted the largest slave escape in American history, the Pearl Incident; that man, Paul Jennings, was one of over a hundred slaves belonging to this man. The wife of this man is often credited with saving a portrait of George Washington from the during the burning of DC; that woman, Dolley, moved with this man to the White House after her husband was elected president in 1808. For ten points, name this Virginian who served as the fourth president of the United States.",
        "answer": "James Madison Jr."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "James Madison lived much of his adult life on this plantation in Orange County, Virginia.",
        "answer": "Montpelier"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A town on the east bank of this river that is home to The Bend Motorsport Park is known as Tailem Bend. Albury and Wodonga are major population centers along this river that is one of the major inflows of Lake Alexandrina. The Murumbidgee River is a tributary of this river that flows through the Snowy Mountains. This river forms a large basin in its country’s southeast with the Darling River. For ten points, name this longest river in Australia.",
        "answer": "Murray River"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Murray River is a primary source of drinking water for this capital of South Australia, which was founded by Colonel William Light.",
        "answer": "Adelaide"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Protests in this country were sparked by a fire at the Cinema Rex that was blamed on the secret SAVAK police, and by failed literacy reforms in this country’s White Revolution. This country was the site of Operation Ajax, where CIA agents deposed Mohammad Mossadegh over his attempts to nationalize oil. Discontent against the new ruler, Mohammad Reza Pahlavi, prompted the implementation of a Islamic republic. Ayatollah Khomeini took power in, for ten points, what Shi’a majority country?",
        "answer": "Iran"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Since Iran became an Islamic Republic, there have only been two Supreme Leaders; this Supreme Leader works with Hassan Rouhani to govern Iran.",
        "answer": "Ali Khamenei"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "As an attorney, this man prosecuted leaders of the “Five Families” during the Mafia Commission Trial. After being diagnosed with prostate cancer, this man withdrew from a 2000 Senate race that was won by Hillary Clinton. This man succeeded David Dinkins in his highest post, in which he said “we’re going to rebuild” during a statement following an event at which his city’s fire department was dispatched to the Twin Towers. For ten points, name this mayor of New York City during 9/11.",
        "answer": "Rudolph “Rudy” Giuliani"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "With the help of Bill Bratton, Giuliani adopted a crime-fighting strategy based on this theory, developed by two social scientists, that explained vandalism’s effect on criminal behavior.",
        "answer": "broken windows theory IHO General Bowl 2017-2018 Round 9"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man issued numerous telegraphs to “cousin Willy” to avoid war during the July Crisis. Sergei Witte advised this man to enact legal reforms in order to stay in power, even though this man’s popularity had plummeted when his soldiers fired on father Georgy Gapon’s protesters on Bloody Sunday. This man issued the October Manifesto in an attempt to pacify disgruntled workers but was soon overthrown in the October Revolution by Lenin’s communists. For ten points, name the final tsar of Russia.",
        "answer": "Nicholas II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of Nicholas II’s promised reforms in the October Manifesto was the establishment of this lawmaking body, which has since evolved into the lower house of Russia’s legislative assembly.",
        "answer": "Duma"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Election of 1800",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Party of Thomas Jefferson that won the election.",
          "answer": "Democratic Republicans do not"
        },
        {
          "question": "Second president who lost the election, a Federalist from New England.",
          "answer": "John Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "Constitutional agreement in which slaves were counted as a namesake fraction of a person that helped decide the election.",
          "answer": "Three-Fifths Compromise"
        },
        {
          "question": "Candidate who tied with Jefferson in the Electoral College.",
          "answer": "Aaron Burr"
        },
        {
          "question": "Amendment passed after it that provided new procedures for electing a president and vice president.",
          "answer": "12th Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of four controversial laws for which the incumbent party was accused of subverting democratic principles.",
          "answer": "Alien and Sedition Acts"
        },
        {
          "question": "South Carolina Federalist vice presidential candidate.",
          "answer": "Charles Cotesworth Pinckney"
        },
        {
          "question": "Delaware Federalist who enabled Jefferson to win by leading abstentions.",
          "answer": "James Bayard Sr. IHO General Bowl 2017-2018 Round 9"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Hundred Years War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "English king whose claim to the French throne caused it.",
          "answer": "Edward III"
        },
        {
          "question": "French heroine who was burned at the stake for witchcraft.",
          "answer": "Joan of Arc"
        },
        {
          "question": "Inheritance law that the French used to invalidate the English claim by disqualifying female inheritance.",
          "answer": "Salic Law"
        },
        {
          "question": "First battle won by English longbowmen, during which John of Bohemia was killed.",
          "answer": "Battle of Crecy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle won by Henry V on St. Crispin’s Day.",
          "answer": "Battle of Agincourt"
        },
        {
          "question": "1340 naval battle in which the French navy was destroyed.",
          "answer": "Battle of Sluys"
        },
        {
          "question": "Peasant rebellion in northern France named for the term nobles used to refer to its participants.",
          "answer": "Jacquerie"
        },
        {
          "question": "French chronicler who described the history of the war from both sides.",
          "answer": "Jean Froissart IHO General Bowl 2017-2018 Round 9"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Six Day War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Egyptian peninsula on the Red Sea captured by Israel along with Gaza.",
          "answer": "Sinai Peninsula"
        },
        {
          "question": "Egyptian leader, an advocate of Pan-Arabism who nationalized the Suez Canal.",
          "answer": "Gamal Abdel Nasser"
        },
        {
          "question": "One eyed Israeli Minister of Defense who oversaw the capture of East Jerusalem.",
          "answer": "Moshe Dayan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Waterway that provided Israel’s only access to the Red Sea; its closure by Egypt sparked the war.",
          "answer": "Straits of Tiran"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sudanese capital city where a namesake resolution that vowed continued belligerency with Israel was passed.",
          "answer": "Khartoum"
        },
        {
          "question": "American spy ship accidentally targeted by an Israeli airstrike.",
          "answer": "USS Liberty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Israeli general and future prime minister, victor of the decisive Battle of Abu Ageila against Egyptian forces.",
          "answer": "Ariel Sharon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Preemptive Israeli airstrike against the Egyptian Air Force that began the conflict.",
          "answer": "Operation Focus IHO General Bowl 2017-2018 Round 9"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This object may have first appeared when the bishop Sunesen could no longer raise his arms in prayer during a great battle, while other accounts of this object hold that it materialized to turn the tide at the Battle of Lyndanisse. During fighting against the (20 pts)",
        "Estonians, this object supposedly fell from the sky to serve as a rallying banner. This object serves as the world’s oldest continuously used flag and features a (10 pts)",
        "white cross on red background. For ten points, identify this flag used by a country with capital Copenhagen."
      ],
      "answer": "Danish flag"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Large scale pollution in this city have threatened the cleanliness of this city’s Sankey Tank. Several urban projects in this city have to the rise of environmental activists launching the Save Lalbagh protests. The largest celebrations for the Karaga festival occur in this city. The (20 pts)",
        "Namma metro is the main metro system in this city which contains the headquarters of Infosys. The large amount of technology companies in this city have led it to be nicknamed the (10 pts)",
        "Silicon Valley of India. Found in Karnataka, for ten points, name this third most populous city in India."
      ],
      "answer": "Bangalore"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An area called Seisia is often referred to as the “Gateway” to this body of water. Musicians Seaman Dan and Christine Anu are members of an indigenous group of islanders named for this body of water. The Endeavour Strait is in the southern portion of this body of water, which is home to the (20 pts)",
        "Prince of Wales Island. This body of water is directly north of the Cape York Peninsula. This body of water connects the Arafura Sea with the (10 pts)",
        "Coral Sea. To the north of Queensland is, for ten points, name this strait that separates Australia from Papua New Guinea."
      ],
      "answer": "Torres Strait"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The pose of this work’s central figure is thought to pay homage to both the Earth and the divine. This work influenced Le Corbusier’s concept of “Modulor.” A work by Giacomo Andrea da Ferrara contains similarities to this one but was criticized for incorrectly positioning the (20 pts)",
        "navel. Principles from Polykleitos’ canon were adapted into this work, whose creator accompanied it with notes like “the space that lies between the (10 pts)",
        "legs is an equilateral triangle.” Book 3 of De Architectura inspired, for ten points, what sketch of the human body’s ideal proportions, made by Leonardo da Vinci?"
      ],
      "answer": "Vitruvian Man IHO General Bowl 2017-2018 Round 9"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man gained fame for successfully prosecuting an organized crime group known as Murder Inc. He prosecuted Richard Whitney for embezzlement and lost one election to the man who made him a district attorney, Herbert Lehman. This governor of New York successfully prosecuted (20 pts)",
        "Lucky Luciano and was opposed by conservative senator Robert Taft. He ran an uninspired presidential campaign while his opponent criticized the (10 pts)",
        "Do-Nothing Eightieth Congress. For ten points, name this man who the Chicago Daily Tribune mistakenly claimed had defeated Truman in 1948."
      ],
      "answer": "Thomas E. Dewey"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This body of water served as the debut ground for a weapon titled “No Alternative,” which consisted of gunpowder hidden in reed mats that would then be dropped on the enemy. A naval battle in this body of water was fought over the town of (20 pts)",
        "Nanchang and concluded when fire ships were successfully activated against the tower ships of Chen Youliang. This body of water was the site of the (10 pts)",
        "largest naval battle in history during the Red Turban Rebellion at the end of the Yuan dynasty. For ten points, name this lake in Jiangxi Province, the largest freshwater lake in China."
      ],
      "answer": "Lake Poyang"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this city, Amedy Coulibaly killed four Jewish hostages during an attack on a kosher supermarket. The Kouachi brothers carried out an attack in this city in response to a series of (20 pts)",
        "cartoons satirizing Mohammad; that attack on the Charlie Hebdo offices in this city occurred in the same year that airstrikes in Raqqa prompted on attack that saw 90 people killed in the (10 pts)",
        "Bataclan theater alone. That attack targeted a stadium where Francois Hollande was watching a sports match. For ten points, name this city that was targeted in a series of 2015 attacks."
      ],
      "answer": "Paris"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These constructs were first accurately surveyed by William Gowland, who became known as Japan’s father of archaeology. After Suanin banned human sacrifices, Haniwa (20 pts)",
        "terracotta figures were placed inside these constructs instead. A period of rule by the Yamato clan is alternatively named for these constructs, which were constructed in keyhole shaped (10 pts)",
        "mounds following the Yayoi period. For ten points, name these constructs that were exemplified by the Japanese kofun and contained the remains of emperors."
      ],
      "answer": "Japanese tombs IHO General Bowl 2017-2018 Round 9"
    }
  ]
}